Barry O'Neill



Princeton, NJ, USA







Profile

Experienced software developer, specializing in enterprise Java-based web applications. Extensive background in the full software development lifecycle, including requirements gathering, design, coding, testing, debug and maintenance.

Technical Skills

Languages/Markup Java, Perl, Shell, Python, HTML, JavaScript DHTML/DOM, XML, JSON, CSS **APIs/Frameworks** Android, J2EE, Servlets, JSP, Struts, JSE, Spring, JDBC, Hibernate, iText PDF

Android, J2EE, Servlets, JSP, Struts, JSF, Spring, JDBC, Hibernate, iText PDF, LDAP/JNDI, J2ME, XMLBeans, Apache Axis, Oracle Fusion Middleware/ADF.

DHTML/DOM, AJAX, vFiles, Aspose, Eclipse BIRT, Diango

Tools Eclipse, Intellij IDEA, Android Studio, JDeveloper, PyCharm, Ant, JUnit, Maven,

Selenium, MagicDraw UML, AndroMDA, Mantis, Bugzilla, Cruise Control, Hudson

Web/Appservers Apache, IIS, Tomcat, Websphere, Weblogic, Oracle Application Server

Databases/SQL Oracle, MySQL, MS SQL Server, PostgreSQL Source Control Git (GitHub), Subversion, Perforce, CVS

Administration Windows, Linux, Email (Postfix, SLOX), Networks (Cisco Ethernet, ISDN, PIX

Firewall)

Professional Experience

Freelance Software Developer

Aug 2013 - Present

Hosted Graphite, Dublin, Ireland - hostedgraphite.com

- Design, prototyping and development of an Android app for graph dashboard monitoring.
- The development of a Java API to support the app, which is planned for a separate release.
- Implementation of new features for a customer-facing web application.
- Design and implementation of a utility to import data from AWS Cloudwatch.

Software Engineer, Customer Systems

Dec 2008 - Aug 2011

Verband der Vereine Creditreform, Leinfelden-Echterdingen, Germany - creditreform.de

- Lead developer for several customer-specific projects with complex workflows, involving J2EE business logic with custom web functionality.
- Collaborated with the software configuration manager on the specification and configuration of our Weblogic, Tomcat, Apache and Oracle DB servers.
- Led the migration of several core CrefoSystem components from Java 1.4 to 1.5, including migration from Weblogic 8 to 10.
- Lead technical role on the "CrefoSystem 2.0" project, using Oracle's Application Developer Framework to deliver Creditreform's newest generation of business information.
- Created a proof-of-concept app (yFiles/AJAX) for visualizing company hierarchy information. This application replaces the legacy applet-based solution, thus vastly simplifying our client's minimum system requirements.
- Lead role on web-based dynamic reporting application, using Eclipse BIRT.
- Developed a Single Sign-On solution for linking sessions across separate application servers.

Professional History (continued)

Software Consultant and Contractor

YouGetItBack, Cork, Ireland - yougetitback.com

- Consulted with YGIB on the day-to-day technical affairs of the company's online presence.
- Provided instruction/supervision of junior developers.
- · Led the overhaul of the online store and tag registration system.
- Designed and prototyped the 'print your own' tag system (iText PDF generation).
- Created the proof-of-concept J2ME implementation of the 'mobile superhero' protection software.
- Oversaw struts/mysql/tomcat/apache/linux configuration, as well as the rollout of upgrades.

Senior Software Developer

Jun 2002 - Oct 2006

TERMINALFOUR. Dublin. Ireland - terminalfour.com

- Lead developer for of many core modules of the flagship 'Site Manager' product.
- Simplified provisioning for many of our larger customers through the introduction of LDAP integration.
- Introduced source control, project structure, and build policies, cutting developer environment setup time in half.
- Designed a more efficient publishing system, resulting in significant savings in publish time.
- Project manager for a year-long project for one of our largest customers, replacing two separate legacy systems with a single web application.
- Designed and developed installation, upgrade and licensing modules which completely changed how our product was delivered to the customer, resulting in huge time savings for both us and the client.
- Supported in-house and customer-based technical staff with the development with our APIs as well as with deployment issues.

Junior Software Developer

Jun 2000 - May 2002

TERMINALFOUR, Dublin, Ireland - terminalfour.com

- Supported several customers with system, configuration and deployment issues.
- Installed and maintained both internal and on-site equipment.
- Designed and developed custom perl and java-based web applications for customers.
- Wrote a significant amount of technical documentation for our intranet.

Technical Support Representative

Nov 1998 - May 2000

Ireland On-Line/ESAT Telecom (Now: BT Ireland) - btireland.ie

- Provided first and second level technical support to both residential and business customers.
- Trained and supervised new support employees.
- Updated and provided new material for the support intranet.

Education

B.Sc. Computer Applications, Dublin City University, Ireland (2002) - dcu.ie

Other Information

Developer of several published, open-source Android apps (*github.com/barryoneill*)
Sun Certified Web Component Developer (SCWCD 5)
Sun Certified Java Programmer (SCJP 1.4)

Languages: English (Native speaker), German (working proficiency, TELC Zertifikat Deutsch B1)

Nov 2006 – Nov 2008